<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <spell>
    <name>Branding Smite [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Evocation, Paladin</classes>
    <level>2</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 bonus action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <text>The next time you hit a creature with a weapon attack before this spell ends, the weapon gleams with astral radiance as you strike. The attack deals an extra 2d6 radiant damage to the target, which becomes visible if it's invisible, and the target sheds dim light in a 5-foot radius and can't become invisible until the spell ends.

At Higher Levels:
When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 2nd.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 219</text>
    <roll>2d6</roll>
    <roll>3d6</roll>
    <roll>4d6</roll>
    <roll>5d6</roll>
    <roll>6d6</roll>
    <roll>7d6</roll>
    <roll>8d6</roll>
    <roll>9d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Commune With Nature [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Divination, Druid, Ranger, Druid (Arctic), Druid (Forest), Paladin (Ancients), Barbarian (Totem Warrior)</classes>
    <level>5</level>
    <school>D</school>
    <ritual>YES</ritual>
    <time>1 minute</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <text>You briefly become one with nature and gain knowledge of the surrounding territory. In the outdoors, the spell gives you knowledge of the land within 3 miles of you. In caves and other natural underground settings, the radius is limited to 300 feet. The spell doesn't function where nature has been replaced by construction, such as in dungeons and towns.

You instantly gain knowledge of up to three facts of your choice about any of the following subjects as they relate to the area:

	• terrain and bodies of water
	• prevalent plants, minerals, animals, or peoples
	• powerful celestials, fey, fiends, elementals, or undead
	• influence from other planes of existence
	• buildings

For example, you could determine the location of powerful undead in the area, the location of major sources of safe drinking water, and the location of any nearby towns.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 224</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Feeblemind [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Enchantment, Bard, Druid, Warlock, Wizard</classes>
    <level>8</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>150 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a handful of clay, crystal, glass, or mineral spheres)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <text>You blast the mind of a creature that you can see within range, attempting to shatter its intellect and personality. The target takes 4d6 psychic damage and must make an Intelligence saving throw.

On a failed save, the creature's Intelligence and Charisma scores become 1. The creature can't cast spells, activate magic items, understand language, or communicate in any intelligible way. The creature can, however, identify its friends, follow them, and even protect them.

At the end of every 30 days, the creature can repeat its saving throw against this spell. If it succeeds on its saving throw, the spell ends.

The spell can also be ended by greater restoration, heal, or wish.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 239</text>
    <roll>4d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Meld Into Stone [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Transformation, Cleric, Druid, Druid (Mountain)</classes>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>YES</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>8 hours</duration>
    <text>You step into a stone object or surface large enough to fully contain your body, melding yourself and all the equipment you carry with the stone for the duration. Using your movement, you step into the stone at a point you can touch. Nothing of your presence remains visible or otherwise detectable by nonmagical senses.

While merged with the stone, you can't see what occurs outside it, and any Wisdom (Perception) checks you make to hear sounds outside it are made with disadvantage. You remain aware of the passage of time and can cast spells on yourself while merged in the stone. You can use your movement to leave the stone where you entered it, which ends the spell. You otherwise can't move.

Minor physical damage to the stone doesn't harm you, but its partial destruction or a change in its shape (to the extent that you no longer fit within it) expels you and deals 6d6 bludgeoning damage to you. The stone's complete destruction (or transmutation into a different substance) expels you and deals 50 bludgeoning damage to you. If expelled, you fall prone in an unoccupied space closest to where you first entered.

Prone:
	• A prone creature's only movement option is to crawl, unless it stands up and thereby ends the condition.
	• The creature has disadvantage on attack rolls.
	• An attack roll against the creature has advantage if the attacker is within 5 feet of the creature. Otherwise, the attack roll has disadvantage.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 259</text>
    <roll>6d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Pass Without Trace [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Abjuration, Druid, Ranger, Cleric (Trickery), Druid (Grassland)</classes>
    <level>2</level>
    <school>A</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (ashes from a burned leaf of mistletoe and a sprig of spruce)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <text>A veil of shadows and silence radiates from you, masking you and your companions from detection. For the duration, each creature you choose within 30 feet of you (including you) has a +10 bonus to Dexterity (Stealth) checks and can't be tracked except by magical means. A creature that receives this bonus leaves behind no tracks or other traces of its passage.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 264</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Speak With Animals [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Divination, Bard, Druid, Ranger, Cleric (Nature), Paladin (Ancients), Barbarian (Totem Warrior)</classes>
    <level>1</level>
    <school>D</school>
    <ritual>YES</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <text>You gain the ability to comprehend and verbally communicate with beasts for the duration. The knowledge and awareness of many beasts is limited by their intelligence, but at minimum, beasts can give you information about nearby locations and monsters, including whatever they can perceive or have perceived within the past day. You might be able to persuade a beast to perform a small favor for you, at the DM's discretion.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 277</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Speak With Dead [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Necromancy, Bard, Cleric, Cleric (Knowledge)</classes>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>N</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>10 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (burning incense)</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <text>You grant the semblance of life and intelligence to a corpse of your choice within range, allowing it to answer the questions you pose. The corpse must still have a mouth and can't be undead. The spell fails if the corpse was the target of this spell within the last 10 days.

Until the spell ends, you can ask the corpse up to five questions. The corpse knows only what it knew in life, including the languages it knew. Answers are usually brief, cryptic, or repetitive, and the corpse is under no compulsion to offer a truthful answer if you are hostile to it or it recognizes you as an enemy. This spell doesn't return the creature's soul to its body, only its animating spirit. Thus, the corpse can't learn new information, doesn't comprehend anything that has happened since it died, and can't speculate about future events.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 277</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Speak With Plants [2014]</name>
    <classes>School: Transformation, Bard, Druid, Ranger</classes>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self (30-foot radius)</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <text>You imbue plants within 30 feet of you with limited sentience and animation, giving them the ability to communicate with you and follow your simple commands. You can question plants about events in the spell's area within the past day, gaining information about creatures that have passed, weather, and other circumstances.

You can also turn difficult terrain caused by plant growth (such as thickets and undergrowth) into ordinary terrain that lasts for the duration. Or you can turn ordinary terrain where plants are present into difficult terrain that lasts for the duration, causing vines and branches to hinder pursuers, for example.

Plants might be able to perform other tasks on your behalf, at the DM's discretion. The spell doesn't enable plants to uproot themselves and move about, but they can freely move branches, tendrils, and stalks.

If a plant creature is in the area, you can communicate with it as if you shared a common language, but you gain no magical ability to influence it.

This spell can cause the plants created by the entangle spell to release a restrained creature.

Source:	Player's Handbook p. 277</text>
  </spell>
  </compendium>